A Guide to the Gubernatorial Appointment Registers of the Virginia Secretary of Commonwealth, 1998-2002
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Gubernatorial Appointment Registers of the Virginia Secretary of Commonwealth, 1998-2002
The Library of Virginia
51138
2 cu.ft. (2 boxes)
Virginia. Office of the Secretary of Commonwealth
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
The folders must be reviewed before being served. Privacy protected information is considered closed for 75 years after date of record creation per Code of Virginia 42.1-78. Types of records restricted include, but are not limited to: forms with social security numbers.
Acquisition Information
Transferred on 9 January 2014 by the Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth, 1111 East Broad Street, 4th Floor, Richmond, Virginia, 23219.
Historical Information
The Office of the Secretary of the Commonwealth has evolved from early colonial times when there existed a Secretary of the Colony. Thomas Nelson held the position of the first Secretary of Virginia in 1776. Early Secretaries were elected by the public. An Act of the General Assembly in 1920 changed the election to a joint vote of the General Assembly. In a 1930 Act the duties of the Secretary were redefined with the Secretary of the Commonwealth serving as the ex officio secretary of the Governor, as custodian of many official State records, and as keeper of the Greater and Lesser Seals of the Commonwealth. The office of the Secretary has gradually acquired other functions, such as: service of out-of-state civil process; appointment and regulation of notaries public; and registration and oversight of lobbyists. The Office became a gubernatorial appointment subsequent to a 1958 Act of the Assembly. The Secretary of the Commonwealth is under the jurisdiction of the Governor's Office. The Secretary is appointed by the Governor for a term of four years. Currently the Secretary of the Commonwealth is responsible for gubernatorial appointments, clemency and restoration of civil rights requests and extraditions. Additional activities include: serving as ex officio Secretary to the Governor; serving as keeper of the seals of the Commonwealth; compiling and publishing the annual Blue Book; commissioning and regulating notary publics, including the publication of a Notary Handbook and conduct of disciplinary hearings; promulgating the lobbying disclosure requirements, registration of lobbyists, and recording of lobbying reports; servicing the civil process of out-of-state defendants and other parties; and authenticating and certifying the records of the courts and of any state agency.
Anne P. Petera was appointed by Governor James S. Gilmore (1998-2002) to serve as Secretary of the Commonwealth, effective January 23, 1998. Petera served until the end of Gilmore's administration in January 2002.
Scope and Content
Gubernatorial appointment registers, 1998-2002, concerning gubernatorial appointments to state boards and commissions during the administration of Governor James S. Gilmore (1998-2002). Includes correspondence, appointment tracking sheets, curriculum vitae and resumes, and appointment worksheets.
Arrangement
Arranged chronologically.
Contents List
- 1998 January-May (Box 1, Folder 1)
- 1998 June-July (Box 1, Folder 2)
- 1998 July (Box 1, Folder 3)
- 1998 August (Box 1, Folder 4)
- 1998 September (Box 1, Folder 5)
- 1998 October (Box 1, Folder 6-7)
- 1998 November (Box 1, Folder 8)
- 1998 December (Box 1, Folder 9)
- 1998, Misc. (Box 1, Folder 10)
- 1999 January-March (Box 1, Folder 11)
- 1999 March (Box 1, Folder 12)
- 1999 April (Box 1, Folder 13)
- 1999 May-June (Box 1, Folder 14)
- 1999 July-August (Box 1, Folder 15)
- 1999 August (Box 1, Folder 16)
- 1999 September (Box 1, Folder 17)
- 1999 October (Box 1, Folder 18)
- 1999 October (Box 2, Folder 1)
- 1999 November-December (Box 2, Folder 2)
- 2000 January (Box 2, Folder 3)
- 2000 February-March (Box 2, Folder 4)
- 2000 March (Box 2, Folder 5)
- 2000 May-June (Box 2, Folder 6)
- 2000 July (Box 2, Folder 7)
- 2000 August (Box 2, Folder 8-9)
- 2000 September (Box 2, Folder 10)
- 2000 October-December (Box 2, Folder 11)
- 2001 January (Box 2, Folder 12)
- 2001 February-March (Box 2, Folder 13)
- 2001 March (Box 2, Folder 14)
- 2001 April-August (Box 2, Folder 15)
- 2001 September-October (Box 2, Folder 16)
- 2001 November-December (Box 2, Folder 17)
- 2001 December (Box 2, Folder 18-20)
- 2002 January-June (Box 2, Folder 21)